### Zain-ul-Abideen

**E-Mail:**<u>zaintahir7173@gmail.com</u> **CELL #:** 0092-336-0362138

Address: A-3211 Gulshan-e-Hadeed Phase 2 Bin Qasim Town Karachi.



### **CAREER PROFILE**

Energy & Environmental Engineer with working experience in environmental services industry & Health Safety Environment. Skilled in HSE Implementation, HSE inspections, Communication, Quality Management, Environmental Auditing, Environmental Awareness, Environmental Monitoring, Solid Waste Management and Environment Impact Assessment. Strong community and social services professional with a Continuing Master's Degree in Engineering Management focused in Environmental Management from NED University of Engineering and Technology.

### AREAS OF EXPERTIES

## Environmental Impact Assessments

Baseline Data Collection, Analysis, Interpretation & Documentation of following key Environmental Health & Safety Aspects:

- Air Quality Monitoring.
- Ground/Surface Water Monitoring/Sampling.
- Microbiological Analysis of Water.
- Soil Sampling.
- Terrestrial Flora/Fauna Sampling.
- Aquatic Flora/Fauna Sampling.
- Human Health & Safety Assessments.

Development & Documentation of Environmental Management & Monitoring Plan including following sections:

- Mitigation/Compliance Budget.
- Monitoring Requirements.
- Monitoring Parameters.
- Monitoring Frequency.
- Implementation Responsibility

## Environmental Audits/Inspections

Field Investigations and Documentation of Environmental Audit/Inspection Reports to Facilitate Clients in:

- Environmental Compliance
- Identification of Management System Implementation Gaps.
- Identification of Corrective Actions.

### Research & Development:

Analysis of current market trends & need assessment of different sector related to environmental sustainability to create new services & products as per client's need and requirement.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# "Environmental Engineer" (Global Environment Management Services, Karachi, Pakistan)

(March 2017 - Till Date)

#### Responsibilities:

To assist project manager to ensure timely completion of EIA/IEE & Environmental Audit Assignments by supervising following teams:

- o Environmental Monitoring Team
- Social Survey Team

To provide end to end environmental health and safety solutions for different sectors by leading EIA/IEE, Environmental Audit & World Bank Project Team

# "Environmental Engineer" (Global Environment Management Services, Tharparkar, Pakistan)

(Sep 2016- March 2017)

Client Organization: 1. Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company, Islamkot Thar. (SECMC)

2. Engro Powergen Thar Limited, Islamkot Thar. (EPTL)

## Project: Independent Environmental Monitoring Consultant Responsibilities:

- Preparing site monthly Environmental Monitoring report and submit to Sindh Environmental Protection Agency
- Checking compliance status
- Providing Energy & Environmental Solutions
- Conducting Socio Economic Surveys
- Implentation on Enivironmental monitoring plan
- Site surveys and reporting
- Designs and Training
- Design of water/waste water treatment and distribution networks
- Implementation of EMS (ISO 14001) and EnMS (ISO 50001)
- Hazardous waste management
- Air Pollution Control Solutions
- Clean Manufacturing
- Pollution Prevention & Chemical Management

# "Health, Safety & Environmental Engineer" (Construction Project of Procter and Gamble Pakistan)

(Jan 2016 – August 2016)

### Responsibilities:

- Monitoring the implementation health, safety and environment management procedures
- Prepare HSE reports (daily, weekly, Monthly etc.)
- Provide advice on selection and effective use of PPEs
- Inspection of fire detection and prevention system and equipment
- Documentation
- Prepare and deliver Daily toolbox talk at site
- Check the permit to work and ensure the people are being complied with permit to work system
- Ensure PPEs is being used

### **QUALIFICATION**

2017	MEM (	(Environmental	Management)
------	-------	----------------	-------------

NED University of Engineering and Technology, Karachi. (Continue)

2015 BE (Energy and Environment) 1<sup>st</sup> Division

Dawood University of Engineering & Technology,

**3.2 CGPA** 

Karachi.

2011 Intermediate - Pre-Engineering (A) Grade

HSC - Govt Degree College Malir Cantt, Karachi

71 %

2009 Matriculation - Science (A1) Grade

SSC - Young Scholars Public School, Karachi

85.4%

### THESIS-WORK AND PROJECTS

- Waste Water Treatment using UASB Technology(FYP)
- Case Study of KB Feeder lake Kotri
- Analysis of Ambient Air Quality of Karachi City

#### **CERTIFICATES'S & COURSE'S**

- **IOSH Managing Saftely**
- Scaffolding Safety
- Hazard Communication
- Confined Space Safety

### **CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP ATTAINTED:**

- Building Environmental Awareness for a Sustainabale Future by US Consulate
- One day workshop on "Hazards And Risk Assessment"
- One day Workshop on "ISO: 9001:2008"
- One day Workshop on "ISO:1400:2004"
- One day Workshop on "OSHA's :18001
- One day Workshop on "Project Management Professionals"
- One day Workshop on "Renewable Energies and Energy Efficiencies"

### **COMPUTER LITERACY**

- MS Office 2000-2016, (Microsoft Word, Microsoft Excel, Microsoft PowerPoint)
- MS-DOS, MS Windows All version

### PERSONAL INFORMATION

Father's Name **Tahir Mehmood** 

**Nationality** Pakistani

Date of Birth 26th January, 1993 N.I.C. No 42501-9170841-5

**Marital Status** Single

### **REFERENCES**

References will be provided upon request.